Guide to the G. Hope Summerell Chamberlain papers, 1821-1946 RL.11492
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
G. Hope Summerell Chamberlain papers
1821-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chamberlain, Hope Summerell
RL.11429
10 Linear Feet
G. Hope Summerell Chamberlain was an author, artist, and civic worker, of Raleigh (Wake Co.) and Chapel Hill (Orange Co.), N.C. Letters from 1821 to 1946 concern family matters for the most part but also reflect Chamberlain's career as an author of local history and her work at Duke University as the house counselor of Pegram House. Scattered earlier letters include one from Herbert J. Hagermand of the American Embassy at Saint Petersburg, 1889; letters on the Russo-Japanese War, 1905; and letters from John Spencer Bassett, 1903. The remainder of the collection includes genealogical material on the Chamberlain family; clippings of articles about Chamberlain and her books; drafts of some of her writings; a copy of a journal of a trip to Europe in 1792-1793; diary of Chamberlain's trip to Europe in 1929; and personal diaries, 1923-1926 and 1943.
Biographical / Historical
G. Hope Summerell Chamberlain was an author, artist, and civic worker, of Raleigh (Wake Co.) and Chapel Hill (Orange Co.), N.C.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The G. Hope Summerell Chamberlain Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift.
Collection Overview
Letters from 1821-1946 concern family matters for the most part but also reflect Chamberlain's career as an author of local history and her work at Duke University as the house counselor of Pegram House. Scattered earlier letters include one from Herbert J. Hagermand of the American Embassy at Saint Petersburg, 1889; letters on the Russo-Japanese War, 1905; and letters from John Spencer Bassett, 1903. The remainder of the collection includes genealogical material on the Chamberlain family; clippings of articles about Chamberlain and her books; drafts of some of her writings; a copy of a journal of a trip to Europe in 1792-1793; diary of Chamberlain's trip to Europe in 1929; and personal diaries, 1923-1926 and 1943.
College students -- Conduct of life; Europe -- Description and travel -- 19th century; Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905; Bassett, John Spencer, 1867-1928; Duke University. Pegram Residence Hall; Hagermand, Herbert J.; Chamberlain family; Caraleigh Phosphate and Fertilizer Company
- G. Hope Summerell Chamberlain papers, 1821-1946; 1
  - Correspondence, 1821-1904 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1905-1914 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1920 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1925 March (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1925 April-1932 July (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1932 Aug.-1935 Oct. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1935 Nov.-1937 July (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1937 Aug.-1938 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1946, undated (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 11)
  - Diaries, 1792-1793, 1923 (Box 11)
  - Diaries, 1878, 1924-1927, 1929, 1943-1944 (Box 12)
  - Notebook, 1929 (Box 12)
  - Writings: Oh Call Back Yesterday; What's Done and Past (Box 13)
  - Writings: Life Story of Elisha Mitchell; This Was Home (Box 14)
  - Writings: Old Days in Chapel Hill (Box 15)
  - Writings: Done in a Corner; A Little Sketch; A Study of Presbyterianism; Two Wake County Editors (Box 16)
  - Misc. Writings (Box 16)
  - Writings: Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Writings: Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Miscellany (Box 18)
  - Printed Material, 1828-1939 (Box 18)
  - Printed Material, 1940-1946, undated (Box 19)
  - Clippings (Box 19)
  - Clippings (Box 20)